長野県立品の皆さん、おはようございます。
先生、なんで立品?
いや、この間行ったらね、とってもトウモロコシがおいしかったんですよ。
素晴らしいところですよね、あそこは。
ラジオ英会話、ハートでつかめ、英語の極意、講師の尾西、ひろとです。
Hey everyone, this is Akina Rosa.
And I'm David Evans.
Well, I like these stories better than his corny jokes.
Oh, God.
さあ、それでは早速始めていきましょう。
Lesson 136
説明ルールその2文修飾
今日のキーセンテンスはこちら
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
説明ルールの練習を続けましょう。
今回は場所、時の修飾語句など文修飾について学びます。
Now, let's check out today's dialogue.
Desperate Rats' band manager, Stacey, is talking to Bill.
It seems that Derrick had a request to appear on the Kelly King Show.
Bill, did you hear that Derrick was invited to Kelly King's talk show?
Yeah, Derrick told me.
Are you okay with that?
Sure. People forget that Derek's one of the original members of the band.
I'm the new guy, really.
But he left the band. You're not mad about that?
That's all behind us. He's back now.
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
How do you know?
That's the way it goes with old rockers.
それでは、ダイアログの内容を確認します。
Bill, did you hear that Derek was invited to Kelly King's talk show?
Bill, デレクがケリー・キングのトーク番組への出演を依頼されたのを聞いている?
さあ、Did you hear? 聞いて知っている?っていう決まり文句ですね。覚えていきましょう。
Yeah, Derek told me.
ああ、デレクが教えてくれたよ。
Are you okay with that?
あなたはそれで問題ないの?
これはもう丸ごと覚えてしまって
差し支えのない便利さを持った表現ですね
With これはそのことと一緒にいてOKですかと言っているわけです
Sure, people forget that Derek's one of the original members of the band
I'm the new guy, really
もちろんさ
デレックがこのバンドの発足メンバーの一人だということを
みんな忘れているね
But he left the band. You're not mad about that?
That's all behind us. He's back now.
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
Kore kara wa shinu made boku tachi to issho ni ensou suru darou ne.
How do you know?
どうしてわかるの?
さあ、ここのHow、プロセスを尋ねるWH語でしたね。
That's the way it goes with old rockers.
昔かたきのロックンローラーとはそういうものさ。
Grammar and Vocabulary
文法と語彙のポイントを確認します。
まず確認するのはビルのこのセリフ。
People forget that Derek's one of the original members of the band.
人々はデレクがこのバンドの補足メンバーの一人だということを忘れています。
リポート文の形です。
forget 忘れているの内容をざっと説が説明展開していますね。
ここで使われた that に注目しましょう。
thatのイメージは導く what is thatあれは何といえば聞き手の注意を遠くにあるものに
導くことができますねざっと説でも働きは変わりません forgetと述べてから何を忘れているのかというと
とその内容に正確に滑らかに導くために用いられる補助的要素として働いているんです
ビルのセリフを確認しましょう。
That's the way it goes with old rockers.
それが昔のロックンローラーに合うやり方です。
The way, やり方、方法、なりゆきの後ろに説を並べ、その説明としています。
説明ルール、説明は後ろに置くが生み出す形の一つ。
That's the way life goes.
人生とはそうしたものだ などよく使われます
ちなみにgoのイメージは進んでいく
goは行くという訳語を覚えるだけではなく
ある場所から離れ進んでいく様子をイメージしてくださいね
それではもう一度ダイアログを聞いてみましょう
Bill, did you hear that Derek was invited to Kelly King's talk show?
Yeah, Derek told me
Are you okay with that?
Sure! People forget that Derek's one of the original members of the band.
I'm the new guy, really.
But he left the band. You're not mad about that?
That's all behind us. He's back now.
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
How do you know?
That's the way it goes with old rockers.
会話に役立つ典型表現を身につけましょう。
まずは今日のキーセンテンスを改めて確認します。
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
彼は亡くなる日まで私たちと演奏するでしょう。
英語では状況が生じた場所、時を述べるフレーズは文末な定位置。
それは説明ルール、説明は後ろに置くが働いているからです。
この文で、until the day he diesは、he'll perform with usの時を説明するため、その後ろに置かれているんです。
それでは早速キーセンテンスの練習を始めていきましょう。
時や場所を表すフレーズというのは、語字は日本語と反転します。
しっかりと英語の語順で練習するようにしましょう。
まずは、
He'll perform with us.
どうぞ。
さあ、その後ろに、
ポンと時を示すフレーズで説明する気持ちで、
until 以下をつなげていきます。
He'll perform with us.
Until the day he dies.
はい、OKです。
それでは、その他の例も一緒に身につけていきましょう。
We had lunch at the mall.
私たちはショッピングモールでランチしました。
We had lunch on the second floor.
私たちは2階でランチしました。
場所を示すフレーズを説明の意識で後ろに置きます。
I work out in the morning.
私は朝トレーニングをします。
I work out for an hour.
私は1時間トレーニングをします。
時を示すフレーズも文末に、
説明を展開する意識で
I work outの後ろに置きます。
I can't focus with you looking at me.
あなたが私を見ていたら集中できません。
付帯状況のwith、withで同時に起こっている状況を説明します。
with以降はyouとlooking at meを並べるだけで文的な内容を構成しています。
説明ルールが生み出す形です。
私は車の中で空港に向かっているところです。
I'm in the carを同時、ing形を使い、同時に起こっている状況で説明。
ほら、英語は並べるだけで説明できる気軽な言葉なんです。
それでは、今紹介した表現を、
デイビッドさん、ローザさんと一緒に声に出して練習してください。
All right, everyone. It's time for today's practice.
We'll be using the 説明ルール。
So, please put the explanation at the end.
All right.
Let's practice.
Repeat after us, everyone.
We had lunch at the mall.
We had lunch on the second floor.
Great work. Let's keep going.
I work out in the morning.
I work out for an hour.
Okay, here's the next one.
I can't focus with you looking at me.
Okay, one more.
I'm in the car heading to the airport.
Unlock your potential.
Repetition is the key.
Great work.
Grammar in action.
文習食を含む文を作りましょう。
まずはこちら。
ルーク、彼はちょっと前にロビーにいましたよ。
彼のことを見なかったのですか?
さあ、これをノーヒントできます。
ルーク、彼はちょっと前にロビーにいましたよ。
彼のことを見なかったのですか?
私たちのおすすめは?
Luke, he was in the lobby a minute ago.
Did you not see him?
he was in the lobby no satsume ga a minute ago
boom masu gate ichi desu did you not
no carini didn't you demo okay this year
there are on the crash or less Luke
he was in the lobby a minute ago did you not see him
so they are to give them on that but the statue a
子供たちを近くに置いて話すべきではありません
別の部屋に行きましょう
これもノーヒントで行きましょう
私たちは子供たちを近くに置いて話すべきではありません
別の部屋に行きましょう
私たちのおすすめは
We shouldn't talk with the kids nearby. Let's go to another room.
二重教のwith。
with の後ろは the kids イコール nearby 近くという文的な内容。
では音読練習です。
We shouldn't talk with the kids nearby. Let's go to another room.
それではもう一問 お父さんはドライブウェイにいて車を洗っています 彼の週末の儀式なのです 儀式これはritualと言います お父さんはドライブウェイにいて車を洗っています 彼の週末の儀式なのです
私たちのおすすめは?
Dad's in the driveway washing the car. It's his weekend ritual.
同時に起こっていることを同時に、ING形で気軽に説明。
では音読練習しましょう。
Dad's in the driveway washing the car. It's his weekend ritual.
Hey guys, do you have any rituals?
Oh, for me, Sunday is laundry day.
And folding the laundry after it's clean, that's my ritual.
It's very precise, it's always the same way, and it clears my mind and spirit.
I see. How about you, Rosa?
Well, I have a morning ritual which consists of going out and taking care of the horses.
I see. It's nice to be able to repeat the same thing over and over again.
That's all for today.
Bye!